“在双发飞机可以越洋之前日子真难捱”
"It'll be a cold day in hell before I let twins fly long-haul over-water routes."
这话是Lynn Helms说的
Those were the words of Lynn Helms
他是里根总统时期美国联邦航空管理局(FAA)的主管
—administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration during the Reagan administration.
那时候，美国的商业航班不允许双发飞机飞到
At the time, no commercial american airplane with two engines was allowed to fly anywhere
备降场以外六十分钟航程的距离以外
farther than 60 minutes from a diversion airport.
因为他们认为如果一台发动机失效
The belief was that, if one engine failed,
飞机只能安全地靠仅剩的一台发动机飞行一小时
the other could only safely fly the plane for about an hour.
但这个规则对小型飞机有很大的限制
But this rule severely limited what smaller planes could do.
以纽约到伦敦这种飞跃北大西洋的航线为例
On North Atlantic routes like New York to London,
双发飞机只能飞图中的区域
twin-engine planes could only fly in these areas,
但是不能飞这样的航线
but a direct route looked like this.
当年的解决方法要么是用双发绕远飞
The options were to either fly a twin-engine plane on an inefficient routing,
要么用费油的三发或四发飞机
or fly a inefficient three or four-engine-plane.
这样一来小飞机根本没法走更远一点的近路去飞小城市航线了
There was no place for long-and-skinny routes between smaller cities using smaller planes,
因为这些航线不允许航空公司用双发飞机飞
since airline couldn't legally fly those smaller planes.
这个简单的规则彻底改变了飞机的制造
This one simple rule changed the very way airplanes were built.
因为在60年代，这个60分钟的规定只用在双发飞机上
Now, in the 60's, this 60 minute regulation only applied to planes with two engines.
那么飞机制造商当然可以制造四发飞机
Of course aircraft manufacturers could build quad-engine jets
但它们必须足够大，保证机票能赚回油钱，航司才不会赔
but those had to be huge for airlines to make their money's worth with their high fuel consumption.
那时候747能拉400人
The 747's of the time could carry more than 400 passengers.
所以只能飞大客流量的航线
They could therefore only fly on super high-demand routes
比如纽约飞伦敦，每趟基本都满载
like New York to London to have anyhope of being full.
为了让稍微小一点的飞机也能方便的不间断越洋飞行
In order to start flying more convenient non-stop routes from smaller markets,
飞机得再小一点，又不能违反上面说的规定
planes had to get smaller while still being legally allowed to hop the pond.
于是三发飞机横空出世
That's where trijets came into play.
三发飞机同样不受上面的60分钟限制
With three engines, these planes weren't subject to the same 60-minute regulation as twinjets.
可以轻松飞大西洋航路
They could easily fly any transatlantic route.
所以在七八十年代，你在机场能看见的远程飞机
That's why in the 70s or 80s, the long-haul jets you'd see at airpots were,
绝大多数要么是747，要么是DC-10那样的三发飞机
for the most part, either 747's or trijets like the DC-10.
60分钟限制对跨大西洋飞行的确不方便
This 60-minute regulation was inconvenient for Atlantic Crossings,
但对于太平洋来说，这个规定却改变了夏威夷的发展
but in the Pacific it actually changed how Hawaii developed.
从加州到夏威夷没有任何备降场
There are zero diversion airports between California and Hawaii,
这远远大于上面提到飞机60分钟能飞的航程
so the route isn't even close to covered under the 60-minute rule.
结果就是，当年美国本土飞夏威夷只能用大飞机
As a result, airlines could only fly huge planes between the mainland and Hawaii,
也就是只能飞火奴鲁鲁
which meant that planes could pretty much only fly to Honolulu.
这直接导致夏威夷其他岛屿与美国本土没有任何航空连接
There was virtually no service between the other islands and the mainland,
导致它们很多都被荒废了
which meant the other islands were severely isolated.
这也是为啥最近这几年旅游业一直在开发夏威夷其他的岛屿
That's part of the reason why the tourism industry only picked up on the other islands in recent decades.
最初的时候60分钟限制其实是给活塞螺旋桨飞机定的
The 60 minute rule originated from the days of piston driven propeller aircraft.
因为那些破飞机发动机空中失效概率太高了
With these, it was far more common for engines to just stop working mid-flight.
所以总出事
That's why there were contingency engines.
但这条规则并没有因如今越来越可靠的喷气式发动机而改变
The regulations just didn't adapt to the increased reliability of jet engines.
数据显示每一台喷气式发动机失效，就有117台活塞发动机失效
Statistically, for every failure of a jet engine, there are 117 piston engine failures.
当飞机进入喷气时代，发动机失效就不像当年那么吓人了
Once the jet age rolled in, engine failure just wasn't as much of a concern.
所以在1985年，FAA终于“开恩”
So, in 1985, the FAA begrudgingly granted permission
让美国环球航空的双发飞机——波音767可以直飞波士顿到巴黎航线
to Trans World Airlines to fly their twin-engined 767 direct between Boston and Paris
这条航线上离备降场最远要飞120分钟
—a route taking it up to 120 minutes away from diversion airports.
这是FAA全新的规定的首例应用，称为“ETOPS”——
This was the first example of a brand new FAA certification called ETOPS—
全称“双发延程飞行”
"Extended-range Twin-engine Operational Performance Standards",
简言之“要么飞要么游”
or more colloquially, "engines turn or passengers swim".
航司在飞远程越洋航班之前
Before an airline can fly a long over-water route,
他们得先买一架经过ETOPS认证的飞机
they have to buy a plane with what's known as an ETOPS type rating.
那些飞机安装有额外的通讯系统与灭火系统
Basically that means that the plane was built with adequate redundancies communications systems and fire suppression system
以保证单发失效时的安全
and fire suppression systems to fly safely if one engine fails.
比如说，波音767——第一款得到ETOPS认证的机型
For example, the 767—the first plane to get an ETOPS certification
认证级别为ETOPS-180——最远可以飞离备降场180分钟航程的距离
—has a type rating of 180 minutes meaning it can fly anywhere as long as its 180 minutes from a diversion airport.
但航司拥有ETOPS认证的飞机不代表他们就能进行双发延程飞行
But just because a plane has a type rating doesn't mean an airline can fly it ETOPS.
他们还需要对飞机进行专门的维护，专门的机组、专门的乘务
They have to have a special maintenance plan, a special flight crew, special cabin crew,
专门的签派，专用的燃油以及特别定制的备降旅客安置方案
special dispatchers, special fuel quantities, and special passenger recovery plans,
因为光有一条备降的跑道是不够的
since just because there's a runway doesn't mean that a plane can safely divert,
飞机降落不代表紧急情况解除
since the emergency doesn't end once the plane lands.
比如说阿拉斯加的科尔德湾机场
Cold Bay, Alaska, for example,
看上去的确是一个非常完美的亚洲飞北美航线的备降场
is a perfect diversion airport for routes between Asia and North America.
那个机场美洲只有六次商业航班
It only has six commercial flights per week nowadays,
而且那里之前有个空军基地，所以机场跑道非常长
but as a former Air Force Base it has an enormous runway.
可问题是科尔德湾那个小镇只有108人——太小了
The only issue is that the town of Cold Bay has a population of 108—its tiny.
要是有个飞机来备降，这镇子人口一下子能多一两倍
So any diversions automatically double or triple the amount of people in the small town
这尼玛连床都不够睡，碗筷都不够用
There certainly aren't enough hotel rooms or restaurants to house and feed stranded passengers.
所以航司如果最后决定备降科尔德湾机场
So, if airlines plan to use Cold Bay as a diversion airport,
就必须安排好旅客住哪、喂啥、怎么在48小时内送到目的地
they need to make a plan for how to house, feed, and recover passengers within 48 hours of landing.
去年美国航空公司一架波音787飞机，执飞上海到芝加哥航线
Last year an American Airlines 787 was flying from Shanghai to Chicago,
中途在太平洋上空右发故障
when its right engine had an issue halfway across the Pacific Ocean.
飞机立刻左转备降科尔德湾机场
The plane quickly took a left turn diverting to Cold Bay.
当安排好降落的计划之后
Even before landing the plan was implemented,
飞机上乘务发航班第二餐
as flight attendants served a second meal service early.
飞机安全降落科尔德湾机场后
Just a few hours after safely landing in Cold Bay,
美国的机务即刻从西雅图飞往科尔德湾准备去修飞机
American's mechanics took off from Seattle bound for Cold Bay to start fixing the plane.
与此同时，阿拉斯加航空——美国航空公司的“友商”
while Alaska Airlines, American's partner,
从安克雷奇调遣一架波音737去接被困在科尔德湾的旅客们
sent a 737 from Anchorage to pick up the stranded passengers.
这时，乘务发了之前早已备好的航班第三餐
Meanwhile, flight attendants served the third set of meals they had stocked while waiting on the ground,
同时美国海岸警卫队也为旅客们提供了取暖设备
and the coast guard opened their heated hanger to passengers.
备降十小时后，旅客就已经前往安克雷奇了
Just 10 hours after the emergency landing, passengers were on their way to Anchorage,
在那过夜后，搭乘美国航空公司波音757继续前往芝加哥
where they spent the night before taking an American 757 to Chicago.
这是一个备降旅客安置里教科书般的例子
That was a perfect example of how the passenger recovery plan worked.
航司的快速反应以及完善的安置规划让旅客安全快速的完成了旅程
The quick response and defined plan helped the airline get passengers out safely and quickly.
现在，因为发动机的可靠、大量关键设备的冗余
Now, because of the solid engine reliability, numerous redundancies
以及备降旅客安置计划的完善
and well-designed passenger recovery plans,
航空公司和一些机型可以获得一些非常非常长的ETOPS认证
airlines and airplanes can now receive insane ETOPS certifications.
刚刚备降科尔德湾的波音787梦幻客机，拥有ETOPS-330认证
The 787 Dreamliner, the plane that diverted to Cold Bay, has a type rating of 330 minutes.
也就是说可以飞离备降场最多五个半小时航程
That means it can fly up to 5.5 hours away from a diversion airport.
一些南半球的长途越洋航线
Certain routes over long-ocean stretches in the southern hemisphere
过去只在理论上可以用四发飞机执飞
were theoretically possible in the past with four engine planes,
但经济上根本不允许
but were economically impossible,
因为比如墨尔本飞圣地亚哥，飞机根本坐不满，航空公司简直赔死
since airlines could never fill the large planes on the low-demand city pairs like Melbourne to Santiago.
但有了ETOPS-330认证
With the ETOPS 330 certification,
LATAM航空可以用非常省油的波音787
LATAM Airlines can fly their small 787 economically
在这条客流相对不大的航线上跨太平洋飞行（但仍可盈利）
on this relatively low-demand route across the South Pacific.
空客A350飞机甚至认证到了ETOPS-370
The Airbus a350 is even rated for ETOPS 370
最远可以到达远离备降场六小时十分钟的航程
—it can fly 6 hours and 10 minutes away from diversion airports.
这使得A350可以飞跃除了南极点之外地球的任何地方
This plane can therefore fly everywhere on earth except directly over the South Pole.
这条简单规定的改变让三发、四发飞机一下变成了历史
Because of this simple rule change three and four-engine planes are largely a relic of the past.
波音和空客目前仍然生产的各自唯一的四发飞机
Boeing and Airbus' largest jets are both their only four engine planes in production
就是747和A380
—the 747 and a380
如今北大西洋上几乎所有飞机都是双发的
Nearly all North Atlantic traffic today is on twin-engined planes,
因为有越来越多的小飞机也可以获得ETOPS认证
as smaller and smaller planes get ETOPS certifications.
比如加拿大航空，用ETOPS认证的可爱的A319，最多拉120人
Air Canada, for example, flies their tiny 120 passenger a319 with ETOPS certification
每天一班圣约翰机场到伦敦希思罗机场
daily between St Johns Airport and London Heathrow.
英国航空用更袖珍的A318,飞纽约到伦敦的航线
British Airways even sends the even smaller a318 between New York and London City Airport.
这些航线30年前简直无法想象
These routes would have been unimaginable 30 years ago,
但如今飞机的可靠性
but the reliability of the airplanes of today
使我们不用再为担心小飞机飞越大洋的安全性而担心
mean that we need not fear flying small planes over big oceans.